Guide to the Hiller Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Hiller family papers
1824-1848
MS 280
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.75
(2 boxes)
The papers are made up of the business records and correspondence of Jonathan Hiller and the family papers of his second wife, Abigail Allen Hiller. The records of Jonathan Hiller reflect his activities as a real estate manager and financial intermediary in New Haven between 1836 and 1847. Among his major correspondents are James E.P. Dean, Gerard Hallock, Benjamin Noyes, Seth Perkins Staples and N. Chandos Whiting. In the family correspondence (1824-1842), 161 of the 190 letters are addressed to Abigail Allen Hiller before her marriage in 1843. Another substantial group are the letters of the James Brewster family of New Haven.
Hiller family
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Whitlock's, 1945-1951.
Scope and Contents
The Hiller Family Papers consist of business papers of Jonathan Hiller, and the family and personal papers of his second wife, Abigail Maxcy (Allen) Hiller.
The papers of Jonathan Hiller reflect his activities as a real estate manager and financial intermediary in New Haven between 1836 and 1847. This group contains business correspondence, as well as legal and financial papers. Among Hiller's major correspondents are James E.P. Dean, Gerard Hallock, Benjamin Noyes, Seth Perkins Staples, and N. Chandos Whiting.
The papers of Abigail Maxcy (Allen Hiller) include family correspondence dating from 1824-1842 and other personal papers. The correspondence totals 190 letters; of that, 161 are addressed to Abigail M. Allen [i.e. Abigail Maxcy (Allen) Hiller] and are from various members of the Aldis and Allen families, and from friends. A substantial number of letters are from the James Brewster family of New Haven. Additionally, there are letters addressed to her sister, Sarah Ann (Allen) Buffum (4 of which are from Abigail; the others are from school friends and relatives); and letters to and from members of the Allen family (5 by unidentified writers).
Abigail Hiller's other papers consist of poems, notes on various religious and historical subjects, a draft of a talk to be given before the Temperance Society, a newspaper clipping, and parts of a diary or journal.
For a chart outlining the genealogical relations of the Allen-Hiller family, please consult the Genealogical Chart.
The Hiller Family Papers were purchased from Whitlock's in 1945.
Biographical / Historical
Jonathan Hiller (1795-1862) worked as a real estate manager and financial intermediary in New Haven, Conn.
Abigail Maxcy (Allen) Hiller (1809-1905), was the daughter of Capt. Samuel and Sarah W. (Aldis) Allen of Medway, Mass. She was educated at Rev. Claudius Herrick's Female Seminary in New Haven, and first employed as a teacher in John E. Lovell's Lancastrian School, New Haven (1828). Following that year, she worked as a tutoress in the families of Jonathan Hiller of New Haven (1831-1835), James Brewster of New Haven (1835-1839), and Welcome Farnum of Waterford (Mendon Parish), Mass. (1841-1842). In 1843 she became the wife of Jonathan Hiller, after the death of Hiller's first wife, Eliza Louise (Browner) Hiller (1798-1842).
For a chart outlining the genealogical relations of the Allen-Hiller family, please consult the Genealogical Chart.
Business; Education; Families; Real property -- Connecticut -- New Haven; New Haven (Conn.); Deeds; Real estate agents; Allen, Aldis Samuel, 1803-1833; Allen, Charles Coffin, 1807-1857; Allen, Eliab Metcalf, b. 1818; Allen, Eliza Martha Wickes, d. 1835; Ames, Martha Jones Hubbard; Barnes, Martha Kimberly; Brewster, Joseph, 1822-1895; Buffum, Sarah Ann Allen, 1811-1880; Cone, Rebecca Daggett Brewster, 1814-1890; Dean, James Edmond Prior, b. 1800; Gadcomb, Mary Ann; Hallock, Gerard, 1800-1866; Hiller, Abigail Maxcy Allen, 1809-1905; Hiller, Jonathan, 1795-1862; Metcalf, Ann Benton; Metcalf, Electa; Noyes, Benjamin; Scovill, Samuel, 1834-1902; Smalley, Julia Catherine Marvin, b. 1811; Staples, Seth Perkins, 1776-1861; Whiting, Nathaniel Chandos, 1808-1884; Brewster family
- Inventory, 1824-1848
  - Hiller Family Papers
    - Business Papers of Jonathan Hiller
      - Correspondence
        - Bacon, J. G. (Box 1)
          General
          A.L.S. to Mr. Hiller, Jan. 27, 1842
        - Bacon, Orphia (Box 1)
          2 A.L.S. to J. Hiller, July 27, 1844, and [N. d.]
        - Bangs, Richards, and Platt (Box 1)
          A.L.S. to P. &, W. Noyes, Nov. 9, 1840
        - Berthoud, Nicholas (Box 1)
          A.L.S. to J. Hiller, June 8, 1839
        - Brainerd, Tyrus (Box 1)
          2 A.L.S. to T. Hiller, Aug. 25; Dec. 16, 1840
        - Burgess, D. (Box 1)
          A.L.S. to J. Hiller, June 6, 1839
        - Carter, O.C.B. (Box 1)
          A.L.S. to J. Hiller, Jan. 27, 1840
        - Clark, Nathaniel R. (Box 1)
          Certificate of guardianship for Dwight Hiller, Nov. 7, 1839
        - Dean, James Edmund Prior, 1800- (Box 1)
          60 A.L.S. to the following.
          Bradley, Lewis, July 30, 1840 (1)
          Gaston, Nelson H., May 17, 1839 (1)
          J. Hiller (58),
          1839, Jan. 25; Feb. 6, 13, 16; Mar. 10; Apr. 11, 15; 16; May 10, 17, 29; June 15, Sep. 19, 20, 21; Oct. 9, 10, 18, 24, 31; Dec. 3, 4, 10
          1840, Jan. 4; Feb. 10, 19; Mar. 2,(2), 6, 9;(2), 14, 30; Apr. 1, 17; June 3, 26; July 22, 30; Aug. 1, 31; Sep. 1; Oct. 16, 20; Nov. 17; Dec. 2, 27
          1841, Jan. 25, 26, 29; Feb. 8,
          Also, 7 undated ALS
        - Douglas, James (Box 1)
          3 A.L.S. to J. Hiller, Sep. 28; Oct. 1, 1839, Jan. 7, 1848
        - Elliot. W. H. (Box 1)
          A.L.S. to J. Hiller, Feb 1, 1847
        - Foster, Eleazer Kingsbury (Box 1)
          A.L.S. to James. E. Dean, Oct 9, 1839
        - Fisher, A[bijah] (Box 1)
          2 A.L.S. to J. Hiller, Feb. 10; Mar. 25, 18[illegible]
        - Gaston, George W. (Box 1)
          A.L.S. to J. Hiller, Oct. 31 1844
        - Gaston, N[elson] H. (Box 1)
          2 A.L.S. to H. Hiller, Oct. 6, 1838, Aug. 22, 1839
        - Goodrich, Chauncey A. Recommendation for Wm. G. Webster, December 30, 1840 (Box 1)
        - Greene, William P. Jr. (Box 1)
          A.L.S. to J. Hiller, Dec. 26, 1843
        - Hall, Melissa A., Mrs. (Box 1)
          A.L.S. to J. Hiller, Apr. 4, 1840
        - Hallock, Gerard, 1800-1866 (Box 1)
          65 A.L.S. to J. Hiller.
          1838, Jan. 2; Apr. 12; July 25, 27, 31; Aug. 1, 2, 3; Oct. 19; Dec. 1, 18.
          1839, Mar. 26; Apr. 13, 22; July 4, 9, 15; Sep. 20; Dec. 26
          1840, Jan. 6,21; Mar. 21; Apr. 3, 6, 22, 23, 28; May 2, 14; June 11, 26;July 8, 10; Nov. 6; Dec. 7, 31
          1841, Jan. 6, 19; Feb. 2, 6, Mar. 5; Apr. 13, undated (included in no.)
        - Hill, Charles, H. (Box 1)
          A.L.S. to Nathanic. Whiting, Oct. 8, 1838
        - Hiller, Jonathan, 1795-1862 (Box 1)
          2 A.Df. and 1 Df. of J. Hiller to Dr. Neil Arnott (1), G. Hallock (1), and Ceeley (1)
        - Hotchkiss, Horace R. (Box 1)
          2 A.L.S. to J. Hiller, May 18, 1838, and undated
        - Houghton & Co. (Box 1)
          A.L.S. to [Johnson 8 Green]?, Apr. 21, 1838
        - Hunt & Noyes (Box 1)
          A.L.S. to J. Hiller, June 7, 1839
        - Hurd, S. F. (Box 1)
          A.L.S. to J. Hiller, Feb. 10, 1841
        - Joceiyn, Nathaniel, 1796-1881 (Box 1)
          2 A.L.S. to J. Hiller, June 19, 1837, Dec. 11, 1839
        - Law, William A. (Box 1)
          3 A.L.S. to J. Hiller, June 1, 1840, Jan. 4, 1841, and. undated
        - Lee, W. S.? (Box 1)
          A.L.S. to J. Hiller, undated
        - Marsh, Ralph (Box 1)
          A.L.S. to J. Hiller, Jan. 22, 1841
        - Mix, Henry (Box 1)
          A.L.S. to J. Hiller, Oct. 25, 1839
        - Musgrave, Richard (Box 1)
          ALL.S. to J. Hiller, Oct. 12, 1839
        - Noyes, Benjamin (Box 1)
          22 A.L.S. to J. Hiller, all undated
        - Page, Stephen (Box 1)
          A.L.S. to J. Hiller, Feb. 24, 1839
        - Phoenix, Alexander (Box 1)
          A.L.S. to J. Hiller, Mar. 3, 1846
        - Reynolds, William A. (Box 1)
        - Scovill, Samuel (Box 1)
          4 A.L.S. to J. Hiller, Mars. 18; June 13, Nov. 10,1840, Jan 6, 1841
        - Seeley, Ebenezer, 1793-1844 Y1814 (Box 1)
          2 A.L.S. to J. Hiller, Mar. 1; July 8, 1840
        - Paine, John (Box 1)
          A.L.S. to J. Hiller, Mar. 20, 1838
        - Paine & Spalding (Box 1)
          A.L.S. to J. Hiller, Feb. 28, 1837
        - Sherman, T[haddeus] (Box 1)
          A.L.S. to J. Hiller, no date
        - Sickels, Daniel E. (Box 1)
          A.L.S. to J. Hiller, Oct, 1838
        - Smith, Simeon P. [Added to A.L.S. from Noah Coe] (Box 1)
          A.L.S. to J. Hiller, Feb. 9, 1838
        - Sounsbury, J.D. & Co. (Box 1)
          A.L.S. to J. Hiller, Apr. 9, 1844
        - Staples, Seth Perkins, 1776-1861 (Box 1)
          4 A.L.S. to J. Hiller, May 27, 28; July 26, 1839 Mar. 30, 1840
        - Tallman, G. C. (Box 1)
          2 A.L.S. to J. Hiller, Sep. 20, 29, 1838
        - Tallman, William M. (Box 1)
          A.L.S. to J. Hiller, Feb. 26, 1839
        - Treat, A[water] (Box 1)
          A.L.S to J. Hiller, June 20, 1840
        - Warren, W. (Box 1)
          A.L.S. to J Hiller, undated
        - Welpley, James Davenport, 1817-1872 (Box 1)
          2 A.L.S., one each to Mrs. Church, Nov. 16, 1837, and J. Hiller, Oct. 10, 1867
        - Whiting, N[athan] Chandos, 1808-1884 (Box 1)
          8 A.L.S. to J. Hiller. June 22, May 18, 1838, Oct. 16, 1839, and undated
        - Whitney, H[enry] (Box 1)
          A.L.S. to J. Hiller, Jan. 2, 1841
        - Young, Levi Huntington (Box 1)
          A.L.S to J. Hiller, Sep. 30, [1841]?
      - Legal and Financial papers (Box 2)
    - Letters and Papers of Abigail Maxcy (Allen) Hiller
      - Correspondence, 1824-1842
        - Letters addressed to Abigail M. Allen [i.e., Abigail Maxcy (Allen) Hiller] from various members of the Aldis and Allen families and friends (161) (Box 2)
        - Letters from the James Brewster family (25) (Box 2)
        - Letters addressed to Abigail Hiller's sister, Sarah Ann (Allen) Buffum (Box 2)
          Includes 4 letters from Abigail and others from school friends and family.
        - Letters to and from members of the Allen family (Box 2)
          Includes 5 letters from unidentified writers.
      - Miscellaneous Papers
        - 5 poems (Box 2)
        - Notes on various religious and historical subjects (Box 2)
        - Draft of a talk before the Temperance Society (Box 2)
        - Newspaper clipping, "to the Editors from the Temperance Ladies." Daily Herald, New Haven, 1835 December 31 (Box 2)
        - Parts of a diary or journal kept in New York (2 p.), 1832 November 27 and 1833 January 29 (Box 2)
        - Parts of a diary kept in Hartford, Conn. and Medway, Mass. (4 p.), 1839 December 12 - 1842 (Box 2)